A Guide to the William D. Ligon Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #3203
William D. Ligon Papers 1935-1947
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
3203
ca. 1450 items
William D. Ligon
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library on May 18, 1949 by William D. Ligon, Jr. of New York City, New York.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 3,000 items, (13 Hollingers and 15 oversize bound volumes), ca. 9 linear shelf feet), ca. 1907-1949, chiefly the genealogical correspondence and research of William D. Ligon, Jr. concerning the Ligon family. The collection contains correspondence, newsclippings, photographs, post cards, photostats, forms, genealogical charts, book reviews, Christmas card albums, and printed material, much of it mounted in bound volumes and scrapbooks. Also present is the typescript and illustrations for the book The Ligon Family and Connections, the product of all of the research and genealogical inquiries conducted by Ligon through his correspondence.
Much of the information concerns the first and second Ligon reunions, in Richmond, Virginia, and Washington, D.C. respectively, William D. Ligon's visit to England in 1938, and the Ligon kin in England, especially the Royal Family. A copy of the two volume published work can be found in the Rare Books Division (see CS 71. L724 1947). According to Ligon, the founder of the family in Virginia, was Colonel Thomas Ligon; [Lygon] who came to Henrico County, Virginia, in 1641. Thomas Ligon married Mary Harris, daughter of Captain Thomas Harris, who arrived in Virginia in 1611 from Essex, England. Other related families include: Beauchamp, Berkeley, Corbin, Harris, and Savage.
Container List
- PAPERS OF WILLIAM D. LIGON, JR
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr., 1912, 1926-1936 Jun; (7 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr., 1936 Jul-1937 May; (7 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr., 1937 Jun-Nov; (6 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr., 1937 Dec-1938 Sep; (5 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr., 1938 Oct-1943; (5 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr., 1944-1947; (6 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr. (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence between William D. Ligon, Jr. and Alice Ligon Jeanblanc, 1930-1941 (Box Box 7)
  - Correspondence of William D. Ligon, Jr. (England File), 1936-1938 (Box Box 7)
  - The Ligon Family and Connections - Preface, Contents, and Pages vii-406, 1947; (3 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - The Ligon Family and Connections - Pages 407-1335, 1947; (5 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - The Ligon Family and Connections - Pages 1336-2158 and Index, 233 p., 1947 (Box Box 9)
  - The Ligon Family and Connections - Pictures, 1947; (2 folders) (Box Box 10)
  - The Ligon Family and Connections - Omitted Chapter & Illustrations, 1947 (Box Box 10)
  - Corbin and Harris Families in England and Virginia (Box Box 10)
  - Ligon Family Records, n.d. (Box Box 10)
  - Magna Charta by John S. Wurts, Part VII, Pedigree 3V by William D. Ligon, Jr., pages 2218-2223, 1954 (Box Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Ligon Family Data, including Reunions, 1937-1938, n.d. (Box Box 11)
  - Printed Material, 1937-1947 (Box Box 11)
  - Proceedings in Two Sections The Ligon Family and Kinsmen Association, 1937, 1939; (2 volumes) (Box Box 11)
  - Records & Data obtained from members of the Ligon Family, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Reviews re The Ligon Family and Connections by William D. Ligon, Jr., 1948-1949 (Box Box 12)
  - Wills and Other Legal Documents re the Ligon Family - Copies, (4 folders) (Box Box 13)
- OVERSIZE SCRAPBOOKS & ALBUMS
  - 1 Christmas Card Album, 1941
  - 2 Christmas Card Album, 1942
  - 3 Christmas Card Album, 1943
  - 4 Christmas Card Album, 1944
  - 5 Christmas Card Album, 1945
  - 6 Christmas Card Album, 1946
  - 7 Christmas Card Album, 1947
  - Photostats (bound) of Colonial and other records
  - 9 Photostats (bound) of Virginia and English records relating to the Ligon, Berkeley, Savage, etc. Families
  - 10 Photostats (bound) largely from Burke's Peerage, Landed Gentry, Extinct Peerage
  - 11 Photostats (bound) largely from Burke's The Commoners, Extinct Peerage, Nash's Worcestershire and Visitations
  - 12 Scrapbook re Ligons and their kin both in England and America, especially the Royal Family, ca. 1930-1947
  - 13 Scrapbook re Ligon kin, mostly in America & the marriage of W.D. Ligon, Jr. and Ellen L. Singleton, ca. 1907-1944
  - 14 Scrapbook of Photographs & Post Cards re the First (Richmond, Virginia) and Second (Washington, D.C.) Ligon Reunions and Ligon's Visit to England, 1937-1938
  - 15 Scrapbook of Visit to England, and Ligon Reunions at Madresfield Court & in the United States, 1938-1939
- GENEALOGICAL CHARTS
  - Full size photostat of Beauchamp-Lygon Family Chart, prepared by Sir William Lygon, 7th Earl Beauchamp for Second Ligon Family Reunion in Washington, D.C. October 13, 14, 15, 1938 (Oversize Oversize Tray 4)
  - Chart - "Some Royal Kin of the Ligons", n.d. (Oversize Oversize Tray 4)
  - Chart - "Berkeley-Ligon", n.d. (Oversize Oversize Tray 4)
  - Chart - "Lygon-Beauchamp", n.d. (Oversize Oversize Tray 4)
  - Blank Chart for Family Tree, n.d. (Oversize Oversize Tray 4)
  - The Ligon Family and Kinsmen Association Resolution to Sir William Lygon, 8th Earl Beauchamp, as President of the Association, 1939 Jun 12 (Oversize Oversize Tray 4)